<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>science around us | Jennifer Jahncke</title>
    <link>/tag/science-around-us/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/science-around-us/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>science around us</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/logo.JPEG</url>
      <title>science around us</title>
      <link>/tag/science-around-us/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gradient Field</title>
      <link>/project/gradient-field/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/gradient-field/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;To help us visualize 3D functions, there are methods to bring the function down a dimension to give you a little taste of how it’s behaving. One of these methods is gradient fields. Gradient fields represent the maximum rate of change of a 3D function at a point in space. You know those maps of mountain ranges that have all the concentric curves representing altitude? It’s kind of like that, but with some extra info. (Those maps are a little closer to contour maps, which are another method for visualizing three dimensional functions in two dimensions.) Calculating a vector field involves taking a given three dimensional function and calculating “grad f” – yielding a general vector equation. Each coordinate you plug into grad f will give you a little vector describing the behavior of that point. Calculating a bunch of these vectors gives you a pretty vector field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cortical Connections</title>
      <link>/project/cortical-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/cortical-connections/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The cortex of a human brain is complicated. It’s broken into 6 layers, of which several are broken down further into sublayers. Layer 4 receives primary input from lower brain areas. The other areas are all talking to each other or shipping information out or receiving information from higher areas. Without all of these feedback/feedforward connections we would be left unable to make inferences about the world. Let’s say you were looking at a nice, round penny. Primary visual cortex (V1), located at the back of the forebrain, is shipping information up the assembly line about the orientation of each the coins edges. A higher area receives that information and sends a query back down to V1: “circle?” V1 shouts back in agreement, the prediction checks out. Right now the coin is still just an abstract shape - what is it’s significance? Let’s send it up to a higher area. This new area scans for clues and sends back down a new query: “penny?” V1 checks it out…yes! Now we send the information all around the brain to pull out associations and understand the context and form new commands. The information will probably make a stop in the prefrontal cortex to ask what we’re doing with the penny. It might also stop in motor cortex to coordinate movements to interact with the coin. This is all a gross oversimplification of Predictive Coding. The basic idea is that through all of these interconnected brain regions communicating with each other, we are able to parse out information about the world that we would otherwise be blind to if limited to just one processing region.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joint Probability</title>
      <link>/project/joint-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/joint-probability/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;A and B are two separate events, but not necessarily completely separate. Sometimes A and B can happen together. The probability of that occurring is given by &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(P(A \cap B)\)&lt;/span&gt;: the joint probability. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(P(A \cap B)\)&lt;/span&gt; can be a pain to calculate; it’s easiest to deduce visually, but that isn’t always possible. However, in the special case in which A and B are known to be mutually exclusive (that is, they never occur together), you know that the joint probability is automatically zero: knowing something about A says nothing about B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One roundabout way of finding the joint probability is by multiplying the probability of B occurring by the probability A occurring when you already know that B has occurred (the conditional probability). Not very direct, but really informative about the world. It’s hard to predict the probability of just one event occurring, but if you know that its “joint” event already occurred, you know so much more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arc Length</title>
      <link>/project/arc-length/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/arc-length/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Math is everywhere. Here, the wilted shrub forms an arc. Draw a triangle with the tangent line as the hypotenuse, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\Delta x\)&lt;/span&gt; as the base, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\Delta y\)&lt;/span&gt; as the height. The length of the hypotenuse represents an approximation for the length of that portion of the curve. By adding up all of those small hypotenuses, you can calculate the area of the whole arc. Tangent lines represent a linear approximation for a curve, but only near the point where it hits the curve. Even two tangent lines that touch the curve at fairly close points diverge to an extreme extent as you move away from the points around which they’re centered. It’s only through the use of infinite tangent lines that we can accurately measure an arc in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Area</title>
      <link>/project/area/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/area/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Finding the area under one curve involves taking the integral of that curve over the interval of interest: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\int_{a}^{b}{f(x)dx}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to find the area between two curves (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(f(x)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(g(x)\)&lt;/span&gt;), you start by taking the integral of the top curve and subtract from that the un-wanted area - the area under the bottom curve. One more step: find where the two curves intersect. That will give you the bounds to use for the integral (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Center Surround</title>
      <link>/project/center-surround/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/center-surround/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The back of your retina is lined with light-sensitive rods and cones. These photoreceptors catch the light and send the light information to bipolar cells, who then send it to retinal ganglion cells (RGCs). It’s here, at the RGCs, that the chemical signal is turned into an electrical one that can be sent to the brain. First stop: the lateral geniculate nucleus (LGN) in the thalamus. The thalamus contains a whole slew of nuclei (collections of cells), each representing a different sense. (Example: the medial geniculate nucleus is for hearing.) The LGN then shoots the visual information up to primary visual cortex (V1) for basic processing. From V1 the information is sent to higher processing centers to extract more details about the visual scene and to form associations with previous memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each step in the hierarchy deals with a more complicated concept. Spots of light becomes lines, which become curves, etc. But the receptive field of the RGC is worth noting. These cells are very particular about the stiumulus they need to see in order to fire. Here, you can see how a so-called “off-center” RGC receptive field looks. This cell will fire maximally when there is light illuminated only in the “surround” portion of the receptive field, with the center remaining in darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
