<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Jennifer Jahncke</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/logo.JPEG</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Penis Girl Observer</title>
      <link>/project/the-penis-girl-observer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/the-penis-girl-observer/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;the-pg-observer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self isolation during the COVID19 pandemic lockdown has impacted us all differently. A lot of us are baking bread and raising sourdough starters. Some of us (ie. me) are becoming collectors of graffiti tags. In order to try to get myself moving during the lockdown I started going on long walks around Portland. I saw a “Penis Girl” tag and thought it was funny so I snapped a picture. Soon I began seeing Penis Girl (PG) tags all over the place. After three months of collecting I accrued over 100 unique tags. It’s gotten to the point that I can’t really focus on anything when I’m around town because I’m busy scanning for Penis Girl tags. Soon enough I was noticing patterns and learning about Penis Girl. This page is a summary of what I’ve found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;pg-territory&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;PG Territory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The territory here is going to be heavily impacted by the fact that I have not been systemmatically collecting tags and thus there are going to be more tags in the areas that I frequent and I’ll miss tags in areas that I don’t explore. The initial pattern that I noticed was that PG tags were most densely concentrated in SE Portland, less dense in NE Portland, and almost none in North Portland. Then I started noticing more around the riverfront and bleeding into the west side more and more. There is a high concentration of tags on Steel Bridge though I have also found tags on Hawthorne Bridge and Burnside Bridge, just less concentrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/project/the-penis-girl-observer/index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;style&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Style&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the PG tags are just “normal” text with a few distinguishing characteristics: the loop on the “P”, the “N” that almost looks like a “U” sometimes, and the curl on the “L”. They also always write the “e” as lowercase whereas all the other letters are uppercase. Some of the PG tags are in a bigger “bubble” text style. In this case the “R” has a face. This style is much less common (9 out of 123 PG tags are in the bubble style).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;style.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;recurring-patterns-is-penis-girl-more-than-one-person&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Recurring Patterns: Is “Penis Girl” more than one person?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty early on I started to notice that PG tags were more than just “Penis Girl”. There were recurring symbols accompanying the tag. I began to wonder if maybe Penis Girl is more than just one “Girl”. These tags vary from tag to tag. Could be some kind of signature? Below are the recurring symbols:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-circle-a-anarchy-symbol&#34;&gt;The “circle A” anarchy symbol&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;circle-A.png&#34; style=&#34;width:70.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;atf&#34;&gt;ATF&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ATF.png&#34; style=&#34;width:70.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pc&#34;&gt;PC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;PC.png&#34; style=&#34;width:70.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I started seeing some “PC” tags that looked &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; different - the “C” had a little line on it. Was this PC the same PC? (I still don’t know.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;PC-line.png&#34; style=&#34;width:70.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I had been sitting with the idea that maybe Penis Girl was multiple people. And then I saw it: a “Penis Crew” tag. Penis &lt;em&gt;CREW!&lt;/em&gt; The style was consistent with the PG tags so I was confident it was a PG tag. Moreover…PC stands for Penis Crew! &lt;strong&gt;It’s multiple people!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pcrew.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;suspected-pg-tags&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Suspected PG Tags&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the George Floyd murder, tagging and graffiti started to increase (and the city’s drive to cover up/scrub away tags also increased) with the civil unrest. I noticed a couple of postings that…looked PG-like to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;suspected.png&#34; style=&#34;width:50.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The characteristic “P” and the anarchy symbols…I think it’s PG/PC!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;occassional-added-flair&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Occassional Added Flair&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a PG tag is more than just “Penis Girl” or “PC” or whatever. Here are some spotted tags with a little something extra to them. Hard to pick a favorite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;sprinkles.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-pg-copycat&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The PG Copycat&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently I have started spotting tags where the style is not consistent with &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; PG style. The “P” is wrong. The capitalization is wrong. They’re just wrong. Is there a copycat out there? Or is there a new member of the Penis Crew that is not conforming to style standards??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;pg-copycat.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-about-beanz&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What about Beanz?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, there are very few PG tags in North Portland. There is, however a high density of Beanz tags in North Portland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Beanz/beanz.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there a territory war between PG and Beanz? When I saw this tag in North Portland I started to think that maybe (maybe) there was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Beanz/IMG_9145%20PC%20beanz.JPG&#34; style=&#34;width:50.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I’ve only spotted Beanz in North Portland, where there are almost no PG tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/project/the-penis-girl-observer/index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re in Portland…keep an eye out for PG/PC (and Beanz)!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gradient Field</title>
      <link>/project/gradient-field/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/gradient-field/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;To help us visualize 3D functions, there are methods to bring the function down a dimension to give you a little taste of how it’s behaving. One of these methods is gradient fields. Gradient fields represent the maximum rate of change of a 3D function at a point in space. You know those maps of mountain ranges that have all the concentric curves representing altitude? It’s kind of like that, but with some extra info. (Those maps are a little closer to contour maps, which are another method for visualizing three dimensional functions in two dimensions.) Calculating a vector field involves taking a given three dimensional function and calculating “grad f” – yielding a general vector equation. Each coordinate you plug into grad f will give you a little vector describing the behavior of that point. Calculating a bunch of these vectors gives you a pretty vector field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immunohistochemistry: Adding Color to the Brain</title>
      <link>/project/immunohistochemistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/immunohistochemistry/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered how we make these bright and beautiful images of proteins in the brain? It’s done using a technique called immunohistochemistry, which we also call IHC or immuno. The technique used antibodies to label proteins in fixed tissue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;collage.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:80.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I preserve the brain using formaldehyde. This “fixes” the proteins in place. I then embed the brain in a block of agar and slice it into thin sections. There are several ways to do this but I use a vibrating razor blade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video width=&#34;400&#34; style=&#34;display:block; margin:0 auto;&#34; controls&gt;
&lt;source src=&#34;vibratome.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I split up my sections into different wells. Each well will contain a different combination of antibodies so that I can label different proteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;12-well-plate.JPG&#34; style=&#34;width:80.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of antibodies matters. I need a primary antibody, which recognizes my protein of interest, and a secondary antibody which latches on to the primary antibody. The secondary antibody contains a fluorescent “tag”. This tag is what the microscope sees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;primary.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:80.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to look at multiple proteins in the same tissue section, I can use other fluorescent tags that emit different wavelengths of light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;primary%20and%20secondary.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:80.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that all of my images only have 3-4 different colors in them. That’s because we need to be able to separate the fluorescent tags. If the emitted light of two tags have wavelengths that are too close together we cannot tell them apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;all%20spectra%20ex%20em.PNG&#34; style=&#34;width:90.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I have my antibodies where I want them. Now I mount the tissue sections onto microscope slides and they’re ready to be imaged on the microscope!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;slide-on-scope.JPG&#34; style=&#34;width:60.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The microscope images one “channel” of fluorescence at a time. In this case I used 4 different antibodies for 4 different proteins. (The numbers in the parentheses are the wavelengths of the emitted light from the fluorescent tag.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;single%20channels.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:100.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I can overlay the images on one another to get that beautiful merged image. The coloring in the merged image doesn’t necessarily correspond to the fluorescent tags I used. I can use any color combination I want. These four images are all the same micrograph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;merge.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:90.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! Each step has additional intricacies that I glossed over for the sake of simplicity. There are also a number of different microscopy methods that could be used. These images were all taken using a Zeiss Axio Imager equipped with an apotome system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wanna talk about it? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/thejenjay/status/1262832430886469632?s=20&#34;&gt;Hit up my Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cortical Connections</title>
      <link>/project/cortical-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/cortical-connections/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The cortex of a human brain is complicated. It’s broken into 6 layers, of which several are broken down further into sublayers. Layer 4 receives primary input from lower brain areas. The other areas are all talking to each other or shipping information out or receiving information from higher areas. Without all of these feedback/feedforward connections we would be left unable to make inferences about the world. Let’s say you were looking at a nice, round penny. Primary visual cortex (V1), located at the back of the forebrain, is shipping information up the assembly line about the orientation of each the coins edges. A higher area receives that information and sends a query back down to V1: “circle?” V1 shouts back in agreement, the prediction checks out. Right now the coin is still just an abstract shape - what is it’s significance? Let’s send it up to a higher area. This new area scans for clues and sends back down a new query: “penny?” V1 checks it out…yes! Now we send the information all around the brain to pull out associations and understand the context and form new commands. The information will probably make a stop in the prefrontal cortex to ask what we’re doing with the penny. It might also stop in motor cortex to coordinate movements to interact with the coin. This is all a gross oversimplification of Predictive Coding. The basic idea is that through all of these interconnected brain regions communicating with each other, we are able to parse out information about the world that we would otherwise be blind to if limited to just one processing region.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joint Probability</title>
      <link>/project/joint-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/joint-probability/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;A and B are two separate events, but not necessarily completely separate. Sometimes A and B can happen together. The probability of that occurring is given by &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(P(A \cap B)\)&lt;/span&gt;: the joint probability. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(P(A \cap B)\)&lt;/span&gt; can be a pain to calculate; it’s easiest to deduce visually, but that isn’t always possible. However, in the special case in which A and B are known to be mutually exclusive (that is, they never occur together), you know that the joint probability is automatically zero: knowing something about A says nothing about B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One roundabout way of finding the joint probability is by multiplying the probability of B occurring by the probability A occurring when you already know that B has occurred (the conditional probability). Not very direct, but really informative about the world. It’s hard to predict the probability of just one event occurring, but if you know that its “joint” event already occurred, you know so much more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arc Length</title>
      <link>/project/arc-length/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/arc-length/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Math is everywhere. Here, the wilted shrub forms an arc. Draw a triangle with the tangent line as the hypotenuse, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\Delta x\)&lt;/span&gt; as the base, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\Delta y\)&lt;/span&gt; as the height. The length of the hypotenuse represents an approximation for the length of that portion of the curve. By adding up all of those small hypotenuses, you can calculate the area of the whole arc. Tangent lines represent a linear approximation for a curve, but only near the point where it hits the curve. Even two tangent lines that touch the curve at fairly close points diverge to an extreme extent as you move away from the points around which they’re centered. It’s only through the use of infinite tangent lines that we can accurately measure an arc in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Area</title>
      <link>/project/area/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/area/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Finding the area under one curve involves taking the integral of that curve over the interval of interest: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\int_{a}^{b}{f(x)dx}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to find the area between two curves (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(f(x)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(g(x)\)&lt;/span&gt;), you start by taking the integral of the top curve and subtract from that the un-wanted area - the area under the bottom curve. One more step: find where the two curves intersect. That will give you the bounds to use for the integral (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Center Surround</title>
      <link>/project/center-surround/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/center-surround/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The back of your retina is lined with light-sensitive rods and cones. These photoreceptors catch the light and send the light information to bipolar cells, who then send it to retinal ganglion cells (RGCs). It’s here, at the RGCs, that the chemical signal is turned into an electrical one that can be sent to the brain. First stop: the lateral geniculate nucleus (LGN) in the thalamus. The thalamus contains a whole slew of nuclei (collections of cells), each representing a different sense. (Example: the medial geniculate nucleus is for hearing.) The LGN then shoots the visual information up to primary visual cortex (V1) for basic processing. From V1 the information is sent to higher processing centers to extract more details about the visual scene and to form associations with previous memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each step in the hierarchy deals with a more complicated concept. Spots of light becomes lines, which become curves, etc. But the receptive field of the RGC is worth noting. These cells are very particular about the stiumulus they need to see in order to fire. Here, you can see how a so-called “off-center” RGC receptive field looks. This cell will fire maximally when there is light illuminated only in the “surround” portion of the receptive field, with the center remaining in darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microscope Me Up: Purkinje Cells</title>
      <link>/project/microscope-me-up-purkinje-cells/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/microscope-me-up-purkinje-cells/</guid>
      <description>



</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Thread: Molecular Mechanisms of Non-ionotropic LTD</title>
      <link>/project/a-thread-non-ionotropic-nmda-receptor-signaling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/a-thread-non-ionotropic-nmda-receptor-signaling/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
Preprint featuring one of the projects I worked on during my time as a research assistant! Here we start to put together the molecular signaling pathway downstream of non-ionotropic LTD and spine shrinkage. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/MBSfExBzih&#34;&gt;https://t.co/MBSfExBzih&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
— Jennifer Jahncke (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@thejenjay&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/thejenjay/status/1215690681508757505?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;January 10, 2020&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brain cells form excitatory synaptic connections on structures called dendritic spines. These spines change size/shape as the synapse strenghtens or weakens. This process is known as synaptic plasticity. One form of synaptic plasticity is long-term depression (LTD) in which the synapse weakens and the spine shrinks. The mechanism by which LTD occurs is often taught as being an “ionotropic” process - meaning that it requires the movement of ions. In the case of LTD, calcium flux through the NMDA receptor has been shown over and over again to be crucial. Glutamate binds to the NMDA receptor, calcium fluxes into the cell and binds PP2B/calcineurin, which dephosphorylates AMPA receptors, leading to AMPA receptor endocytosis and synaptic weakening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;ionotropic-ltd.PNG&#34; style=&#34;width:50.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is non-ionotropic LTD? To understand this process you first need to know something about NMDA receptors: they require TWO agonists for the ion pore to open: (1) glutamate and (2) glycine or D-serine. If glutamate binds the receptor in the absence of the co-agonist the pore does not open and no calcium can flow through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;co-agonists.png&#34; style=&#34;width:70.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently-ish (Nabavi et al., 2013) it was found that if glutamate binds WITHOUT the ion pore opening….LTD can still occur. 🤯 (PS - yes, recently-ish was 6-7 years ago…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;navabi.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s no calcium influx! So what is going on? Some FRET experiments showed that the intracellular tails of the NMDA receptor move in response to glutamate binding, even in the absence of a co-agonist. This certainly smells like metabotropic signaling. But people didn’t like calling it metabotropic because NMDA receptors are ionotropic…fine…we’ll call it non-ionotropic signaling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;metabotropic.PNG&#34; style=&#34;width:30.0%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before our paper, the only known players in the non-ionotropic signaling pathway were p38 MAPK, CaMKII, and PP1. Here we parse out the signaling pathway, linking NMDA receptor agonism and the associated conformational change to AMPA receptor endocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;pp1-camkii.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our paper uses 2-photon glutamate uncaging to induce LTP at single spines. This results in reduced synaptic strength (assayed with electrophyiology) and spine shrinkage. We then blocked potential signaling molecules and looked to see if this also blocked spine shrinkage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;nNOS.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we found that CaMKII, nNOS, NOS1AP, p38 MAPK, MK2, and cofilin were all necessary for non-ionotropic spine shrinkage!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;featured.PNG&#34; style=&#34;width:50.0%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; This paper has since been &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jneurosci.org/content/40/19/3741&#34;&gt;published at J. Neuro!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;References:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kauer, J., Malenka, R. Synaptic plasticity and addiction. Nat Rev Neurosci 8, 844–858 (2007). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn2234&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn2234&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valdivielso, J.M., Eritja, A., Caus, M., Bozic, M. Glutamate-Gated NMDA Receptors: Insights into the Function and Signaling in the Kidney. Biomolecules 10 (7), 1051 (2020). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/biom10071051&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/biom10071051&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nabavi S, Kessels HW, Alfonso S, Aow J, Fox R, Malinow R. Metabotropic NMDA receptor function is required for NMDA receptor-dependent long-term depression. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013;110(10):4027-4032. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1219454110&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1219454110&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aow J, Dore K, Malinow R. Conformational signaling required for synaptic plasticity by the NMDA receptor complex. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2015;112(47):14711-14716. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1520029112&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1520029112&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dore K, Aow J, Malinow R. Agonist binding to the NMDA receptor drives movement of its cytoplasmic domain without ion flow. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2015;112(47):14705-14710. &lt;a href=&#34;doi:10.1073/pnas.1520023112&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;doi:10.1073/pnas.1520023112&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stein IS, Park DK, Flores JC, Jahncke JN, Zito K. Molecular Mechanisms of Non-ionotropic NMDA Receptor Signaling in Dendritic Spine Shrinkage. J Neurosci. 2020;40(19):3741-3750. &lt;a href=&#34;doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0046-20.2020&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0046-20.2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soph Talks Science: Cellfie of the Month Sept 2019</title>
      <link>/project/soph-talks-science-sep-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/soph-talks-science-sep-2019/</guid>
      <description>



</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
